Guide to the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council Records
Department of Special Collections
Foreign Bondholders Protective Council records
circa 1930-1988
M1287
Foreign Bondholders Protective Council
99.42 linear feet
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The bulk of this collection consists mainly of negotiation files for each country the Foreign Bondholders staff were monitoring. The rest of the collection is made up of administrative records typical of a non-profit organization, such as Articles of Incorporation and bylaws, board correspondence, minutes, financial statements and reports. The papers in this collection cover the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council from their inception in 1933 to the late 1980s.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Accession number: 2001-340. The collection was donated to Stanford University, Department of Special Collections and University Archives in 2001.
Biography / Administrative History
Under Title II of the Securities Act of 1933, a provision was made for the creation of a Corporation of Foreign Security Holders, to be effective when the President of the United States "finds that its taking effect is in the public interest, and by proclamation so declares." It was contemplated that the activities of the new corporation would be similar to those of the British Corporation of Foreign Bondholders, which has an official status in negotiating with foreign issuers.
The act states that the corporation shall be created "for the purpose of protecting, conserving and advancing the interests of the holders of foreign securities in default, however, President Franklin D. Roosevelt decided that it was not in the public interest to set up a corporation, provided that an adequate private organization could be created instead. To that end, the Secretaries of State and Treasury and the Chairman of the Federal Trade Commission requested the formation of the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council Inc. in 1933 to negotiate with foreign governments on behalf of American holders of defaulted foreign dollar bonds. The Council was a private, non-profit public service organization whose officers, directors, and members served without pay. The Council did not act as the agent nor entered into any kind of agreement with any bondholder.
Other related collections at Stanford University are the main library's copies of the British Corporation of Foreign Bondholders (CFB). The original British records are located in the Manuscripts Section of Guildhall Library, London (collection Numbers 15748-814 and 34586-830).
Scope and Content of Collection
The bulk of this collection consists mainly of negotiation files for each country the Foreign Bondholders staff were monitoring. The rest of the collection is made up of administrative records typical of a non-profit organization, such as Articles of Incorporation and bylaws, board correspondence, minutes, financial statements and reports. The papers in this collection cover the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council from their inception in 1933 to the late 1980s.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Dine, Richard; Petty, John R.; Council of Foreign Bondholders, Inc. (United States). Council.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1. Individual Country Negotiation files (Alphabetically) Series 2. Administrative records Subseries 2.1: Board files Subseries 2.2: Richard Dine files Subseries 2.3: Working files Subseries 2.4: Publications
Series 1. Individual Country Negotiation files (Arranged alphabetically) The first series consists primarily of negotiation files created by the Council staff to monitor each individual country?s political and economic development. The files were originally bound and contained press clippings, correspondence, memos, press releases, and telegrams. Some countries? negotiation files are followed by supplemental reports and agreements and, in a few cases, more focused correspondence.
Processing for the first series occurred at the box level. An exception to this would be the German negotiation files which are more organized due to their size. The German files are arranged alphabetically within the following categories: general negotiation files, cities/states, banks, churches, corporations, utilities and miscellaneous. Scholars should note that the German corporation and German utilities files sometimes contain final signed memoranda of terms, correspondence, etc.
Series 2. Administrative Records The second series consists of routine administrative records created by the day-to-day operations of the Council and their staff. This series has four subseries: board files, Richard Dine?s files, working files, and publications. Some parts of this series were processed at the folder level.
Subseries 2.1, Board files, contains the Articles of Incorporation and bylaws for the Council, meeting agenda packets, correspondence, minutes, press releases, and annual reports. Of interest is a White House press release announcing the creation of the Foreign Bondholders Protective Council in 1933. Also of note is a small, typewritten transcript of President Franklin D. Roosevelt?s pencil memorandum stating he wanted a private organization to represent bondholders rather than a government run corporation.
Subseries 2.2, Richard Dine files, detail the Council?s operations in the 1980s. Since Richard Dine was the Assistant Secretary to the Council, the files contain correspondence (not necessarily written by Dine) regarding selected countries? debts, miscellaneous administrative and board records, and financials. Folder level processing did occur in parts of this subseries.
Subseries 2.3, Working files, contain general correspondence, financial, and tax information.
Subseries 2.4, Publications, contain miscellaneous publications created in the United States and abroad relating to finance and investments. They include United States congressional hearings, scholarly journals, and unpublished academic thesis and research papers.
Related Material
Other related collections at Stanford University are the main library?s copies of the British Corporation of Foreign Bondholders (CFB). The original British records are located in the Manuscripts Section of Guildhall Library, London (collection Numbers 15748-814 and 34586-830).
Container List
- Series 1: Individual Country Negotiation File
  - Africa: general file, 1955-1971 (Box 1)
  - Argentina: negotiation file, 1934- August 1935 (Box 1)
  - Argentina: negotiation file, September-December, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Argentina: negotiation file, 1936-1937 (Box 3)
  - Argentina: Negotiation file, Buenos Aires, 1938-1956 (Box 4)
  - Argentina: Negotiation file, City of Cordoba, 1935-1937 (Box 4)
  - Argentina: Negotiation file, City of Cordoba, 1938-1949 (Box 5)
  - Argentina: Negotiation file, Province of Mendoza, 1937-1947 (Box 5)
  - Argentina: Negotiation file, Santa Fe, 1939-1945 (Box 6)
  - Argentina: contracts, miscellaneous drafts, agreements, various dates (Box 6)
  - Austria negotiation file, 1934-1949 (Box 7)
  - Austria: negotiation file, 1950-1953 (Box 7)
  - Austria: negotiation file, 1953-1956 (Box 8)
  - Austria: negotiation file, 1953-1976 (Box 9)
  - Austria: contributions file, 1958-1966 (Box 10)
  - Austria and the various cities: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 10)
  - Austria and the various cities: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 11)
  - Australia: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 11)
  - Australia and various cities: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 12)
  - Belgium: negotiation file, 1934-1956 (Box 12)
  - Belgium and City of Antwerp: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 12)
  - Bolivia: negotiation file, 1934-1954 (Box 13)
  - Bolivia: negotiation file, 1945-1960 (Box 14)
  - Bolivia: negotiation file, 1960-1977 (Box 15)
  - Bolivia: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 16)
  - Bolivia: inquiry letters, 1968-1989 (Box 17)
  - Bolivia: inquiry letters whose coupons were redeemed 1973-1986 (Box 17)
  - Bolivia: contributions, 1969-1972 (Box 17)
  - Bolivia: legal fees (Box 17)
  - Bolivia: confidential file, 1946-1958 (Box 17)
  - Brazil: negotiation file, 1940-1943 (Box 18)
  - Brazil: negotiation file, 1943-1947 (Box 19)
  - Brazil: negotiation file, 1948-1967 (Box 20)
  - Brazil: negotiation file, index for State of Ceara (Box 21)
  - Brazil: negotiation file, State of Ceara, 1934-1947 (Box 21)
  - Brazil state and cities: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 22)
  - Brazil state and cities: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 22.1)
  - Bulgaria: negotiation file, 1934-1979 (Box 23)
  - Bulgaria: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 23)
  - Canada: negotiation file, 1942-1956 (Box 24)
  - Canada: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 24)
  - Chile: negotiation file, 1935-1937 (Box 25)
  - Chile: negotiation file, 1938-1939 (Box 26)
  - Chile: negotiation file, 1940-1947 (Box 27)
  - Chile: negotiation file, 1948 (Box 28)
  - Chile: negotiation file, 1948-1972 (Box 29)
  - Chile: negotiation file, City of Barranquilla, 1938-1943 (Box 29)
  - Chile: debt readjustment, 1948 (Box 29)
  - Chile: mortgage bank issues, various dates (Box 30)
  - Chile: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 30)
  - China negotiation file, 1919-1956 (Box 31)
  - China negotiation file, 1973-1987 (Box 32)
  - China-Hukuang: negotiation file, 1933-1936 (Box 32)
  - China-Hukuang: negotiation file, 1937-1956 (Box 33)
  - China: inquiry letters, 1975-1985 (Box 33)
  - China: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 33)
  - Columbia: child committee, 1934 (Box 34)
  - Columbia: memorandum sobre el reajuste de la deuda externa en dolares, a largo plazo, 1939 (Box 34)
  - Columbia: negotiation file, 1940 (Box 34)
  - Columbia: negotiation file, 1941-1948 (Box 35)
  - Columbia: negotiation file 1948-1970 (Box 36)
  - Columbia: duplicate documents regarding offers, agreements, various dates (Box 37)
  - Columbia: bank bonds (Box 37)
  - Columbia: unsigned agreements between Antioquia and Clair and Company Inc., 1925 (Box 37)
  - Columbia offer made in 1949 (Box 37)
  - Columbia: original bonds, various cities (Box 37)
  - Columbia: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 37)
  - Columbia: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 38)
  - Congo: negotiation file, 1960-1971 (Box 39)
  - Congo: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 39)
  - Congo: Conventions Belgo-Congolaises, 1965 (Box 39)
  - Costa Rica: negotiation file, 1935-1937 (Box 40)
  - Costa Rica: negotiation file, 1939-1951 (Box 41)
  - Costa Rica: negotiation file, 1955-1972 (Box 42)
  - Costa Rica: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 42)
  - Cuba: negotiation file, 1934 (Box 43)
  - Cuba: negotiation file, 1935-1936 (Box 44)
  - Cuba: negotiation file, 1937 (Box 45)
  - Cuba: index, 1938 (Box 45)
  - Cuba: negotiation file, 1938-1974 (Box 46)
  - Cuba: miscellaneous contracts, agreements, various dates (Box 47)
  - Cuba: inquiry letters, 1971-1983 (Box 47)
  - Czechoslovakia: negotiation file, 1934-1946 (Box 48)
  - Czechoslovakia: negotiation file, 1947-1984 (Box 49)
  - Czechoslovakia: negotiation file, 1965-1988 (Box 50)
  - Miscellaneous drafts, agreements, 1920s (Box 50)
  - Czechoslovakia: Memorandum of Procedure, signed original, May 25, 1984 (Box 51)
  - Czechoslovakia: Final Agreement, signed original, November 26, 1986 (Box 51)
  - Czechoslovakia: inquiry letters, 1960-1986 (Box 51)
  - Czechoslovakia: correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 51)
  - Czechoslovakia Contributions, 1956-1964 (Box 51)
  - Czechoslovakia: Oliner, Jacob, et al v. Czechoslovak socialist Republic, 1982-1987 (Box 52)
  - Czechoslovakia: unfiled negotiation materials, agreements, correspondence, 1980s (Box 52)
  - Czechoslovakia: claims settlement, Act of 1981, 1981-1987 (Box 53)
  - Denmark: negotiation file, 1936-1957 (Box 54)
  - Denmark: miscellaneous drafts, agreements, various dates (Box 54)
  - Dominic Republic: negotiation file, 1925-1939 (Box 54)
  - Dominic Republic: negotiation file, 1933-1934 (Box 55)
  - Dominic Republic: negotiation file, 1940-1952 (Box 56)
  - Ecuador: negotiation file, 1931-1961 (Box 57)
  - El Salvador: negotiation file, 1933-1944 (Box 58)
  - El Salvador: negotiation file, 1945-1946 (Box 59)
  - El Salvador: negotiation file, 1946-1972 (Box 60)
  - El Salvador: contribution file (Box 60)
  - El Salvador: Miscellaneous drafts, agreements, various dates (Box 60)
  - El Salvador: Miscellaneous drafts, agreements, various dates (Box 61)
  - Estonia: league loan contract (Box 61)
  - Estonia: negotiation file, 1934-1972 (Box 61)
  - Finland: negotiation file, 1934-1961 (Box 61)
  - Finland: league loan contract (Box 61)
  - France: correspondence with Adolphe Warner (Box 62)
  - France: league loan contract (Box 62)
  - France: negotiation file, 1934-1956 (Box 62)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1934 (Box 63)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1934-1935 (Box 64)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1935-1937 (Box 65)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1938-1939 (Box 66)
  - Mr. Clark's negotiation file, 1930s (Box 66)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1940-1949 (Box 67)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1949-1951 (Box 68)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1951-1952 (Box 69)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1952-1953 (Box 70)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1953-1954 (Box 71)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1954-1955 (Box 72)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1956-1957 (Box 73)
  - Germany: negotiation file, 1958-1972 (Box 74)
  - Germany: miscellaneous letters taken from negotiation files 1940-1951 (Box 74)
  - Germany: negotiation, 1960-1970 (Box 75)
  - Germany: miscellaneous drafts, reports, and agreements (Box 75)
  - Germany: miscellaneous drafts, reports, and agreements (Box 76)
  - Germany: correspondence regarding United States offers (Box 76)
  - Germany: validation file December 1949-Janurary 1951 (Box 77)
  - Germany: validation file February 1951-July 1953 (Box 77)
  - Germany: validation file August 1953-1960 (Box 78)
  - Statistical reports of validation board for German dollar bonds, 1950s (Box 78)
  - Germany: materials pertaining to federal issues in German negotiations related to the Dawes and Young loan, the Prussia conversion issue and Koka (Box 79)
  - Germany: Young Loan Tribunal Decision, 1980 (Box 79)
  - Germany: materials pertaining to the 5% International (Young) loan agreement of 1930, 1959-1980s (Box 79)
  - Germany: Consolidated Agricultural Loan (Box 80)
  - German Consolidated Agricultural Loan: Hannoversche Landeskreditanstalt (Box 80)
  - German Consolidated Municipal Loans: correspondence, contracts, files and documents (Box 81)
  - German Consolidated Municipal Loans: correspondence, contracts, files and documents (Box 82)
  - German Consolidated Municipal Loans: correspondence, contracts, files and documents (Box 83)
  - Central Bank of German States and Provincial Banks (Box 83)
  - German Cities/states: State of Bavaria: validation file (Box 84)
  - German Cities/states: City of Berlin: validation file (Box 84)
  - German Cities/states: State of Bremen correspondence, 1950s (Box 85)
  - German Cities/states: Bremen coupon problems (Box 85)
  - German Cities/states: State of Bremen negotiation, 1940s-1950s (Box 85)
  - German Cities/states: City of Cologne: validation file (Box 85)
  - German Cities/states: City of Düsseldorf: validation file (Box 85)
  - German Cities/states: City of Duisburg (Box 86)
  - German Cities/states: Frankfurt-on-Main: correspondence, 1950s (Box 86)
  - German Cities/states: Frankfurt-on-Main: miscellaneous contracts, drafts, agreements, various dates (Box 86)
  - German Cities/states: Frankfurt-on-Main: miscellaneous contracts, drafts, agreements, various dates (Box 87)
  - German Cities/states: City of Hamburg (Box 87)
  - German Cities/states: City of Hanover (Box 87)
  - German Cities/states: City of Heidelberg (Box 87)
  - German Cities/states: City of Munich (Box 88)
  - German Cities/states: City of Nuremburg (Box 88)
  - German Cities/states: State of Oldenburg (Box 89)
  - German Cities/states: State of Wurttemberg (Stuttgart) Consolidated Municipal Loan (Box 89)
  - German Building and Land Bank (Box 89)
  - German Central Bank, Series A and B (Box 90)
  - German Central Bank for Agriculture (Landwirtschaftliche Zentral Bank) four different bonds (Box 90)
  - German Central Bank for Agriculture (Box 91)
  - German Central Bank for Agriculture (Deutsche Rentenbank-Kreditanstalt) (Box 92)
  - Municipal Bank of Hessen (two offers) (Box 92)
  - German banks: Provincial Bank of Westfalia (Box 93)
  - German churches: Protestant Church in Germany Welfare Institution (Box 93)
  - German churches: Roman Catholic Church in Bavaria (Box 93)
  - German churches: Roman Catholic Church Welfare institutions (Box 94)
  - German corporations: Allgemeinen Elektricitats-Gesellschaft (AEG): physical assets of AEG factories in Stuttgart and Berlin (Box 94)
  - German corporations: Allgemeinen Elektricitats-Gesellschaft (AEG): physical assets of AEG factories in Stuttgart and Berlin (Box 95)
  - German corporations: Brown Coal Industrial Corporation settlement offer, 1950s (Box 95)
  - German corporations: Georg Von Giesche's Heirs Mining (Box 95)
  - German corporations: German Atlantic Cable Company (Box 95)
  - German corporations: Good Hope Steel and Iron Works (Box 96)
  - German corporations: Hamburg Elevated Underground and Street Railways Corporation (Hamburger Hochbahn Aktiengesellschaft) (Box 96)
  - German corporations:Hansa Steamship Lines (Box 96)
  - German corporations:Harpen Mining Corporation (Box 97)
  - German corporations: Housing and Realty Improvement Company (Box 98)
  - German corporations: Hugo Stinnes Corporation and Industries (Box 98)
  - German corporations: Ilseder Steel Corporation (Box 98)
  - German corporations: Koholyt Corporation (Box 98)
  - German corporations: Mansfeld Mining and Smelting Company (Box 99)
  - German corporations: Miag Mill Machinery Company (Box 99)
  - German corporations: North German Lloyd (Box 99)
  - German corporations: Rhine Main Danube Corporation (Box 100)
  - German corporations: Rudolph Karstadt Incorporated (Box 100)
  - German corporations: Ruhr Chemical Corporation (Box 101)
  - German corporations: Ruhr Housing Corporation (Box 101)
  - German corporations: Siemens' and Halske Stock Corporation (Box 102)
  - German corporations: United Industrial Corporation (VIAG) (Box 102)
  - German corporations: United Steel Works Corporation (Box 102)
  - German corporations: United Steel Works Corporation (Box 103)
  - German corporations: Plan for the treatment of claimants under United States Dollar bond and debenture issues of Vereinigte Stahlwerke Aktiengesellschaft (Box 103)
  - German utilities: Baden Consolidated Municipalities (Box 104)
  - German utilities: Bergmansruh, Brandenburg Electric Power Company, Central German Power Company of German Utilities: Magdeburg (Mitteldeutsches Kraftwerk Magdeburg, A. G.): miscellaneous issues, various years (Box 104)
  - German utilities: Berlin Electric Elevated and Underground Railways Company (Box 104)
  - German utilities: Berlin City Electric Company settlement offer materials (Box 105)
  - German utilities: Consolidated Hydro Electric Works of Upper Wurttemburg settlement offer materials, 1950s (Box 105)
  - German utilities: Dortmund Municipal Utilities settlement offer materials, 1950s (Box 106)
  - German utilities: East Prussian Power Company, Adam Opel, Osram G.M.B.H. Kommanditgesellschaft: miscellaneous issues (Box 106)
  - German utilities: Electric Power Corporation settlement offer materials, 1950s (Box 106)
  - German utilities: General Electric Company, 1920s-1950s (Box 107)
  - German utilities: General Electric Company appraisals (Box 108)
  - German utilities: Hamburg Electric Company Unterelbe (Box 108)
  - German utilities: Province of Hanover (Harz Water Works loan) (Box 108)
  - German utilities: Luneburg Power, Light and Waterworks, Ltd (Box 109)
  - German utilities: Mannheim and Palatinate Electric Companies (Box 109)
  - German utilities: Oberpflaz Electric Power Company (Energieversorgung Ostbayern A. G.) (Box 110)
  - German utilities: Prussian Electric Company (Box 110)
  - German utilities: Rhine-Ruhr Water Service Union (Box 111)
  - German utilities: Rhine-Westphalia Electric Power Corporation (Box 111)
  - German utilities: Rhine-Westphalia Electric Power Corporation cleared file (Box 112)
  - German utilities: Rhine-Westphalia Electric Power Corporation Indentures (Box 112)
  - German utilities: Rhine-Westphalia Electric Power Corporation Indentures (Box 113)
  - German utilities: Ruhr Gas Corporation (Box 113)
  - German utilities: Robert Bosch, G.M. B. H. settlement offer on German external debts, 1950s (Box 113)
  - German utilities: Saxon Public Works contracts (Box 114)
  - German utilities: Saxon State Mortgage Institution (Box 114)
  - German utilities: Vesten Electric Railways Company (Box 114)
  - German utilities: Westdeutsche Kaufhof AG (Tietz) (Box 114)
  - German utilities: Westphalia United Electric Company (Box 114)
  - German utilities: Westphalia United Electric Company (Box 115)
  - Germany misc: confidential files containing figures, correspondence and reports for various German banks, corporations, and utility companies (Box 116)
  - Germany misc: debtors contributions, German offers, 1959-1960 (Box 117)
  - Germany misc: debtors contributions, German offers pending (Box 117)
  - Germany misc: contributions from abroad, Germany, special problems (Box 117)
  - Germany misc: council's offer (Box 117)
  - Germany misc: alien property files, 1947-1953 (Box 117)
  - Germany misc: Return of Assets special file (Box 117)
  - Germany misc: transcript of record to the validation board for German dollar bonds in the matter of Richard H. Abrey, 1955 (Box 118)
  - Germany: Washington DC hearings on validation law for German bonds, 1953 (Box 118)
  - Germany misc: miscellaneous reports and published articles regarding German debt, various dates (Box 118)
  - Germany misc: valid board schedules, 1954-1955 (Box 118)
  - Germany misc: Foreign bondholders council's 1938 report excerpt on Germany and Austria (Box 118)
  - Germany misc: miscellaneous reports and published articles regarding German debt, various dates (Box 119)
  - Germany misc: Some basic aspects of the German debt settlement by H. G. Dernburg, 1953 (Box 119)
  - Germany misc: photographs from Debt Conference Germany and Japan, n.d. (Box 119)
  - Germany misc: informal report by Katie Louchheim, 1953 (Box 119)
  - Germany misc: validation schedule by the German Finance Ministry (Box 119)
  - Germany misc: Richsmark Debts, 1954-1959 (Box 119)
  - Germany misc: mailing list, 1953-1954, 6 microfilm rolls (Box 119)
  - East Germany: negotiation, 1956-1976 (Box 120)
  - East Germany bond inquiries (Box 120)
  - East Germany: miscellaneous drafts, reports, and agreements (Box 120)
  - Great Britain negotiation file, 1934-1946 (Box 121)
  - Greece: negotiation file, 1934-1955 (Box 122)
  - Greece: negotiation file, 1955-1961 (Box 123)
  - Greece: negotiation file, 1962-1969 (Box 124)
  - Miscellaneous papers regarding Greek loans (Box 124)
  - Greece: correspondence regarding League loans 6% and 7% (Box 125)
  - Greece: Hellenic Water Works 4% adjustment (Box 125)
  - Greece: one year treasury notes (Box 126)